Belle Krasne Ribicoff
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Belle Krasne Ribicoff papers
1942-circa 2010, bulk 1945-2004
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Krasne Ribicoff, Belle
1.6 linear feet
The papers of Belle Krasne Ribicoff measure 1.6 linear feet and date from 1942-circa 2010, with the bulk of the collection dating from 1945-2004. Papers include biographical materials; correspondence with artists, art historians, writers, museum directors, and others; individual files relating to Belle and Irving Ribicoff's art collection and the Friends of Abe Ribicoff's campaign for the United States Senate; artwork; printed material, e.g., clippings, announcements, exhibition catalogues, brochures; and photographs. The collection documents Ribicoff's career as an arts editor, critic, and her involvement in civic and arts organizations for the State of Connecticut.
Provenance
The collection was donated by Belle Krasne Ribicoff to the Archives of American Art in 2008.
Related Material
Also found at the Archives of American Art is Belle Krasne's letter to Philip Pavia, May 14, 1954 on microfilm reel 3470.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original material requires an appointment.
Letters from Jean Bazaine to Belle Krasne Ribicoff and sketches of Sarai Ribicoff by William Bailey are access restricted. Their use requires written permission.
Biographical Note
Belle Krasne Ribicoff (b. 1924) lives in Hartford, Connecticut and has served as an arts editor, critic, and university administrator.
Ribicoff was born and raised in New York City. She graduated Phi Beta Kappa with a degree in art history from Vassar College in 1945. After a brief stint with an advertising agency in New York, Ribicoff became Assistant Editor at Magazine of Art (1946-1947), where she developed an interest in contemporary art. She served as editor for such publications as Art News (1948-1949), Art Digest (1949-1954), and Craft Horizons (1954-1955).
In 1955, she married Irving S. Ribicoff (1915-1994), an attorney and moved to Hartford, Connecticut. The Ribicoffs' had two daughters, Dara (b. 1956) and Sarai (1957-1980).
Ribicoff has held various positions at the University of Hartford: Development Director at the Hartford School of Art (1980-1981), Development Liaison to the Office of President (1982-1988), and Associate Vice President for Public Affairs (1980-1983). Belle Krasne Ribicoff has served as a professional volunteer for educational and cultural organizations in Connecticut; she has been involved in efforts to make the arts a part of the school curriculum. She was Vice-President of the Hartford Board of Education (1961-1967; 1965-1971) and was Chairman of the State of Connecticut's Commission on the Arts (1965-1971). Ribicoff is a Life Director at the Hartford Stage Company and a Life Regent at the University of Hartford. She is a Sterling Fellows at Yale University and sits on the President's Advisory Committee at Vassar College.
Belle Krasne Ribicoff has received recognition for her professional and public service contributions by a number of institutions. In 1954, she received the Frank Jewett Mather Award for critical writing from the College Art Association. Other honors have included: Charter Oak Leadership Medal for Distinguished Service (1968), the University of Hartford Medal for Distinguished Service (1995), and the Spirit of Vassar award for outstanding commitment and service to Vassar or another community (2005).
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Belle Krasne Ribicoff measure 1.6 linear feet and date from 1942-circa 2010, with the bulk of the collection dating from 1945-2004. Papers include biographical materials; correspondence with artists, art historians, writers, museum directors, and others; individual files relating to Belle and Irving Ribicoff's art collection and the Friends of Abe Ribicoff's campaign for the United States Senate; artwork; printed material, e.g., clippings, announcements, exhibition catalogues, brochures; and photographs. The collection documents Ribicoff's career as an arts editor, critic, and her involvement in civic and arts organizations for the State of Connecticut.
Biographical materials include documentation of the Buttenweiser Prize awarded to Belle Krasne by the Art History Departmental Honors at Vassar College in 1945 and curriculum vitae.
Correspondence, primarily incoming letters consists of letters, postcards, draft versions, and copies of e-mails. Belle Krasne Ribicoff was friends with many artists; their letters focus on daily activities, work, and the art world. Among the correspondents are Oscar and Eleanor Chelminsky, Joseph Cornell, Piero and Virginia Dorazio, John and Rae Ferren, Helen Frankenthaler, James Fitzsimmons, Adolph Gottlieb, John Graham, Ellsworth Kelly, Frank Modell, George L.K. Morris, Philip Pearlstein, Eero Saarinen, David Smith, and Adja Yunkers. There is substantial correspondence from Ben Benn, Sidney Geist, Leon Hartley, Ralph Rosenborg, and Theodore Roszak. Also found are love letters to Belle Krasne Ribicoff from Jean Bazaine. Many of the artists' letters are illustrated. Of note, are a letter from Carl Holty to J.B. Neumann and an artist's statement written by Adolph Gottlieb.
Ribicoff had a professional and personal relationship with a number of prominent writers, actors, and other individuals known for their work in the arts, such as Edward Albee, Claire Bloom, Peter DeVries, Horton Foote, Elia Kazan, Mark Lamos, Estelle Parsons, Karl Shapiro, Cornelia Otis Skinner, and P.L. Travers. There are letters from museum directors, art historians, and other well-known cultural figures, such as Dore Ashton, Clement Greenberg, Balcomb Greene, Rene d'Harnoncourt, Pierre Matisse, E. P. Richardson, Andrew C. Ritchie, Harry Salpeter, Curt Valentin, and Mark Van Doren. Also found are files of holiday cards, many original artwork; letters to Ribicoff upon her departure from Art Digest; letters from representatives at Storm King Art Center Museum and the Wadsworth Atheneum; and letters from unidentified correspondents.
The Ribicoff collection relates to the personal art collection of Belle and Irving Ribicoff; materials document the purchase and sale of artwork and the lending of artwork for exhibitions. There is a file of petition letters sponsored by the Friends of Abe Ribicoff campaign for the United States Senate.
Original artwork includes prints by Jean Arp and Adja Yunkers and pencil sketches of Sarai Ribicoff by William Bailey. Printed material consists of news clippings; a periodical; exhibition announcements; brochures; an offprint of an article by Cleve Gray; and miscellaneous printed material.
Photographs contain black and white photographs of Belle Krasne Ribicoff, Ben and Velida Benn, Richard Krautheimer, and of the jurors attending the Carnegie International exhibition (circa 1954), including Jean Bazaine, Rico Lebrun, Eric Newton, and James Thrall Soby.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into 7 series:
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1945, circa 2010 (Box 1; 1 folder)
Series 2: Belle Krasne Ribicoff Correspondence, 1942-2007 (Boxes 1, 3; 1.0 linear feet)
Series 3: The Ribicoff Collection, 1949-1988 (Box 1; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 4: Friends of Abe Ribicoff Campaign, 1968 (Box 1; 0.1 linear feet)
Series 5: Artwork, circa 1950s-1978 (Box 1, OV 4; 0.1 linear feet)
Series 6: Printed Material, 1948-2000 (Box 1; 0.1 linear feet)
Series 7: Photographs, 1945-circa 2007 (Boxes 1-2; 0.1 linear feet)
Names and Subject Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects:
Albee, Edward, 1928-; Bloom, Claire, 1931-; De Vries, Peter, 1910-1993; Foote, Horton; Kazan, Elia; Lamos, Mark; Lebrun, Rico, 1900-1964; Parsons, Estelle; Ribicoff, Abraham, 1910-1998; Shapiro, Karl Jay, 1913-; Skinner, Cornelia Otis, 1901-; Soby, James Thrall, 1906-1979; Travers, P. L.(Pamela Lyndon), 1899-1996
Storm King Art Center; Wadsworth Atheneum
Subjects-Topical:
Art, American; Art--Collectors and collecting; Art critics; Editors
Types of Materials:
Christmas cards; Drafts (documents); Illustrated letters; Photographs; Postcards; Prints; Sketches
Names:
Arp, Jean, 1887-1966; Ashton, Dore; Bailey, William, 1930-; Bazaine, Jean, 1904-2001; Benn, Ben, 1884-; Chelimsky, Oscar; Cornell, Joseph; D'Harnoncourt, Rene, 1901-1968; Dorazio, Virginia Dortch; Dorazio, Piero, 1927-; Ferren, John, 1905-1970; Fitzsimmons, James, 1919-1985; Frankenthaler, Helen,1928-; Geist, Sidney; Gottlieb, Adolph, 1903-1974; Graham, John, 1887-1961; Greenberg, Clement, 1909-1994; Greene, Balcomb, 1904-1990; Holty, Carl, 1900-1973; Kelly, Ellsworth, 1923-; Krautheimer, Richard, 1897-; Matisse, Pierre, 1900-1989; Morris, George L. K. 1905-1975; Pearlstein, Philip, 1924-; Richardson, Edgar Preston, 1902-; Ritchie, Andrew Carnduff; Rosenborg, Ralph M., 1913-1992; Roszak, Theodore, 1907-; Saarinen, Eero, 1910-1961; Salpeter, Harry; Smith, David, 1906-1965; Valentin, Curt, 1902-1954; Van Doren, Mark, 1894-1972; Yunkers, Adja, 1900-1983
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Material, 1945, circa 2010, Series 1:; (Box 1; 1 folder)
  This series contains documentation for the Buttonweiser Prize awarded to Belle Krasne Ribicoff by the Art History Department at Vassar College and curriculum vitae.
  - Buttonweiser Prize and Curriculum Vitae, 1945, circa 2010 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Belle Krasne Ribicoff Correspondence, 1942-2007, Series 2:; (Boxes 1, 3; 1.0 linear feet)
  Correspondence spans over sixty years, with the bulk dating from 1949-2007. Belle Krasne Ribicoff's correspondence, mostly incoming letters, consists of letters, drafts, postcards, and copies of e-mails. Some letters are illustrated; a few contain original artwork. Many letters have attachments, such as invoices, price lists, notes, sketches, printed material, clippings, exhibition catalogues, invitations, and photographs.
  Ribicoff was friends with many artists. Their letters to her concern daily activities, work, and the art world. Among the correspondents were Charles Burchfield, Oscar and Eleanor Chelminsky, Joseph Cornell, Piero and Virginia Dorazio, John and Rae Ferren, Helen Frankenthaler, Alberto Giacometti, John Graham, Russell Lynes, Frank Modell, George L.K. Morris, Philip Pearlstein, David Smith, John Von Wicht, Adja Yunkers, among others. There are individual artists' files for Ben Benn, Sidney Geist, Leon Hartley, Arnold Newman, Ralph Rosenborg, and Theodore Roszak. Two items of interest: Carl Holty's letter to J.B. Neumann discusses the use of realism in his work and an artist's statement by Adolph Gottlieb. Marcel Duchamp correspondence consists of two black and white photographs of the artist: a print by Victor Obsatz inscribed to Belle Krasne Ribicoff and a print by Naomi Savage, and a reproduction of an artwork.
  Ribicoff's friends and colleagues included writers, actors, and other well-known individuals associated with theatre and film, such as Edward Albee, Claire Bloom, Horton Foote, Elia Kazan, Peter De Vries, Mark Lamos, Estelle Parsons, Cornelia Otis Skinner, and P.T. Travers. Also found are letters from art historians, museum directors, gallery dealers, such as Dore Ashton, S. Lane Faison, Balcomb Greene, Rene d'Harnoncourt, Pierre Matisse, Andrew C. Ritchie, Harry Salpeter, Curt Valentin and others. Files also contain letters to Belle Krasne Ribicoff from friends and colleagues relating to her departure from Art Digest; letters between Ribicoff and representatives of the Storm King Art Center Museum pertaining to her donation of unpublished letters by David Smith to the museum; and correspondence with the Wadsworth Atheneum. Included is a small file of unidentified correspondents.
  Correspondence, including files with individuals where there is substantive correspondence is arranged alphabetically; letters within the folders are filled in chronological order.
  - A, 1948-2007, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Addams, Charles
    Albee, Edward
    Ashton, Dore and Adja Yunkers
    Arthur Lénars and Cie
  - B-C, 1950-1997 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Bloom, Claire
    Blumenthal, Charles
    Burchfield, Charles
    Carnegie Institute
    Chelminsky, Oscar and Eleanor
    Cisneros, Henry G.
    College Art Association
    Cornell, Joseph
  - D-E, 1954-1981, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    D'Harnoncourt, Rene
    De Vries, Peter
    Dorazio, Piero and Virginia
    Edelman, Maurice
    Ernst, Jimmy
    Evergood, Philip
  - F, 1950-1999 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Ferren, John and Rae
    Fitzsimmons, James
    Foote, Horton
    Frankenthaler, Helen
  - G, 1950-1990 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Gottlieb, Adolph
    Glamer, Fritz
    Graham, John
    Grasso, Ella
    Greenberg, Clement
    Greene, Balcomb
  - H-L, 1950-1997, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Hagenbech, Marguerite
    Holmes, Willard
    Holty, Carl
    Horowitz, Glenn
    J. D. Smith Inter-Ocean, Inc.
    Kappel, Philip
    Katz, Leslie
    Kelly, Ellsworth
    Lamos, Mark
    Lynes, Russell
  - M-P,1942-2004, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Marca-Relli, Conrad
    Matisse, Pierre
    Modell, Frank
    Morris, George, L. K.
    Nesbit, Alexander
    Parsons, Estelle
    Pearlstein, Philip
    Pittman, Hobson
  - R-S,1946-2001, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Richardson, E. P.
    Ritchie, Andrew C. (The Museum of Modern Art, New York)
    Robinson, Frank
    Rowland, Governor John C.
    Ryan, Anne
    Saarinen, Eero
    Salpeter, Harry
    Schlesinger, Arthur, Jr.
    Shapiro, Karl
    Shikler, Aaron
    Skinner, Cornelia Otis
    Smith, David
    Steinberg, Leo
  - T-Y, 1946-1959, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Toscano, Anonimo
    Travers, P. L.
    Valentin, Curt
    Von Wicht, John
    Yunkers, Adja
  - Bazaine, Jean, 1953-1973, (See Box 3) (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Benn, Ben, 1954-1988, undated (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 12-15)
  - Duchamp, Marcel, 1951, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Geist, Sidney, 1953-2005 (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 17-20)
  - Hartley, Leon, 1955-1964, undated (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 21-23)
  - Kazan, Elia, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Newman, Arnold, 1956-2003 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Rosenborg, Ralph, 1955-1992 (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 26-28)
  - Roszak, Theodore, 1951-1962 (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 29-30)
  - Van Doren, Mark,1967-1971 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Holiday Cards, including Original Artwork, 1950-1989 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Letters relating to Belle Krasne Ribicoff's Departure from Art Digest,1954 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Bazaine, Jean,1953-1973 (11 folders) (Box 3, Folder 1-11)
- The Ribicoff Collection, 1949-1988, Series 3:; (Box 1; 0.2 linear feet)
  The Ribicoff Collection consists of records maintained by Belle Krasne Ribicoff on the Ribicoffs' personal art collection. Files document works that were sold or donated and the lending of artwork for exhibitions, mainly to university museums, including the Hopkins Center Art Galleries at Dartmouth College, Trinity College, Vassar College, and Williams College.
  Materials include: correspondence with individuals at museums, galleries, publishers, and framers; loan agreements, exhibition forms, delivery receipts, and an insurance endorsement; receipts and invoices for frames and photographic prints of artwork; receipts for purchase of artwork; and consignment receipt, sales confirmation notice, post sales advice, and remittance advices for sale of artwork; and photographs of artwork.
  - Correspondence, 1954-1982 (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 38-39)
  - Loan Agreements, Exhibition Forms, Receipts, and Insurance Endorsement, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Receipts and Invoices for Frames and Photographic Prints of Artwork, 1955-1977, undated (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Receipts for Purchase of Artwork,1949-1951,undated (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Consignment Receipt, Sales Confirmation Notice, Post Sales Advice, and Remittance Advices for Sale of Artwork, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Lists, 1959-1991, undated (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Various Printed Materials, 1971-1986, undated (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Photographs of Artwork, 1988, undated (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 46-47)
- Friends of Abe Ribicoff Campaign, 1968, Series 4:; (Box 1; 0.1 linear feet)
  Files include petition letters for Abraham Ribicoff's reelection to the United States Senate for the State of Connecticut and a clipping of the campaign advertisement sponsored by the Friends of Abe Ribicoff that appeared in the New York Times featuring the list of signatories to the petition.
  Scattered notes include individuals who had expressed interest in supporting Ribicoff's nomination.
  - Letters in Support of Abe Ribicoff's Reelection to the United States Senate, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Notes, Loose Envelopes, and Clipping, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 49)
- Artwork, circa 1950s-1978, Series 5:; (Boxes 1, OV 4; 0.1 linear feet)
  Artwork includes a color print of a figure by Jean Arp and cover art for Art Digest by Adja Yunkers. There are two pencil sketches of Sarai Ribicoff by William Bailey.
  - Print by Jean Arp, undated (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Cover Art for Art Digest by Adja Yunkers, circa 1950s; (Oversized material housed in Box 2) (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Miscellaneous Sketch, undated (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Sketches of Sarai Ribicoff by William Bailey, 1978; (See OV 4) (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Oversized Cover Art by Adja Yunkers, circa 1950s; (Oversized material from Box 1, Folder 51) (Box 2)
  - Oversized Sketches of Sarai Ribicoff by William Bailey, 1978 (Box OV 4)
- Printed Material, 1948-2000, Series 6:; (Box 1; 0.1 linear feet)
  Printed material houses clippings, mostly reviews of art exhibitions, announcements, exhibition catalogues, and an offprint of an article by Cleve Gray. Included are brochures for the elementary arts education program, Project CREATE directed by Belle Krasne Ribicoff.
  Materials are arranged in chronological order.
  - Clippings, 1979-2000, undated (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Announcements, 1967-1991, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Exhibition Catalogues, 1948-1954, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Brochures, circa 1969 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Offprint, Narcissus in Chaos, Contemporary American Art by Cleve Gray, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, 1951, 2000-2004, undated (Box 1, Folder 59)
- Photographs 1945-circa 2007, Series 7:; (Boxes, 1-2; 0.1 linear feet)
  This series contains black and white prints of Belle Krasne Ribicoff, Ben and Velida Benn, Richard Krautheimer and the Carnegie International jury featuring Jean Bazaine, Rico Lebrun, Eric Newton, and James Thrall Soby.
  Also included are black and white snapshots of Belle Krasne Ribicoff at Vassar College and color snapshots of Ribicoff with unidentified colleagues and friends.
  - Belle Krasne Ribicoff, 1945, undated (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Belle Krasne Ribicoff with Colleagues and Friends, 1940s-circa 2007 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Ben and Velida Benn and Richard Krautheimer, 1963, undated (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Carnegie International Jury, circa 1954; (2 folders; Oversized material housed in Box 2) (Box 1, Folder 63-64)
  - Carnegie International Jury, circa 1954; (Oversized material from Box 1, Folder 63) (Box 2)